Awesome. Great. Thank you so much, Dan.
Um, it's really a pleasure to
participate in this really exciting
class. Uh, so yeah, so I'm excited to
share some of the recent uh advances
around AI agents and especially think
about how we can use these AI agents to
help us to automate and to accelerate
different kinds of scientific
discoveries.
So the broader context of this is that
um AI has been very successful as a tool
in across many different domains of
science and traditionally the way that
we use AI is that you first start with
like a well- definfined scientific
problem right you have a specific target
right and then you can use a specific
like well curated AI tool right to
tackle that well- definfined problem so
an example of this is that if you let's
say if you have a problem of trying to
predict structures or proteins
Right? Then you can use a tool like
alpha fold try to predict in those
structures.
Uh but you need to have like a well-
definfined problem first. And we're
seeing this kind of interesting
conceptual shift over the past year
whereby instead of thinking of AI really
as a tool for solving like a narrowly
defined problem, people are starting to
explore AI as a co-scientist try to
tackle this broader range of research
endeavors, right? all the way from
helping us to generate hypothesis to
designing experiments, analyzing data,
even writing papers. And a lot of that
shift, right, is driven by these
advances in the AI agents, right, which
you have been discussing in this class,
which are essentially systems that we
can then build on top of large language
models that then enables these models to
be able to use different tools like
alpha fold and other domain specific
tools, but also to access additional
resources like different databases and
memories, right? Right. So this then
enables these agents right to become
really co-scientists that can really
help us to uh across this very versatile
kinds of research endeavors.
So what I want to do today in this class
is to uh discuss some of the recent
advances in these AI scientist agents
and I want to share a few concrete
examples right of how these kind of AI
agents can really help us to greatly
accelerate research and discovery. So in
the first example I'll share right so
I'll talk about the virtual lab which is
a work that we uh published um a couple
months ago where we have a team of
different AI agents that collaborate
right to discover new uh new proteins
and new drug candidates and the second
example I talk about paper to agent
which kind of a recent work uh but I'm
very excited about this right where
we're imagining uh turning every
research paper into its own inter
interactive agent try to facilitate
knowledge diss dissemination
and then in the third part I'll talk
about that's actually quite recent
conference that we just uh uh organized
uh which just finished a couple weeks
ago called agents for science. It's the
first conference where both the authors
and also the reviewers are AI agents. So
I'll share some of the findings that we
have from this conference, some of the
highlights and also like some of the
learnings
and what I'll do is that um I'll pause
uh at a few places in um during the
presentation so that uh we can take
questions from the audience uh and then
have a more of an interactive
discussion.
Awesome. Great. So I'll start by talking
about the virtual lab. So the virtual
lab um it's a open source platform that
we built where we have teams of
different AI scientist agents that
interact and work together right so they
collaborate to tackle these open-ended
research problems they can also work and
collaborate with human scientists so the
virtual lab in many ways sort of mirrors
my real lab here at Stanford. So in the
virtual lab there's AI professor agent
and working with the AI professor agent
there are bunch of different AI student
agents with different expertise some
have expertise let's say in
computational biology right or in
machine learning or in imunology and
these AI agents then have their own
group meetings and they can work
together to tackle these research
problems. We also built a school for the
agents whereby the agents can actually
go to the school and then teach themsel
how to become a better researcher. So
I'll explain both the virtual lab and
also the agent school.
So first I'll just explain a bit of how
we interact with the virtual lab agents.
Right? So like a human researcher can
interact primarily by talking to the PI
agent or the professor agent. So for
example I can explain to the PI agent
some description of the project that I'm
interested in. Maybe one project could
be I want to find like a new drug
candidate, right? Or design a new
protein. Another project could be you
know I want to have I have this complex
data set. I want to analyze this data
set, right? Or I want to design a
clinical trial, right? So it could be
very different kinds of projects and
then for each project, right? So the PI
agent will look at that project and then
try to decide by itself like what are
the different areas of expertise that
are needed to tackle that task. So maybe
for this particular task, the PI agent
says okay, it's useful to have a machine
learning agent. It's also useful to have
some expertise in protein engineering,
right? Right? So then it's actually the
job of the PI agent then to train and to
create the sub agents that have each of
those relevant expertise. So for
different projects the PI agent has the
flexibility then to create and train sub
agents with different levels of
different types of expertise. So it's
quite versatile.
I'll come back to and explain in more
detail in two slides right of how that
training and um creation process of the
agent happens. For now, you can think of
each agent basically being like a
frontier language model like a GPD4 or
GPD5 model under the hood. And then we
do additional fine-tuning to teach these
models how to use these specialized
scientific tools like alpha fold and
also have access to these more
up-to-date scientific knowledge.
So after the so all the agents are
automatically created by the PI agent
then after the agents are created then
they can start to have their own group
meetings where all the agents would meet
together right and then come up with the
research plan. They can also have
one-on-one meetings where one of the
agent might meet with a PI agent to
review a subtask. A subtask here could
be like analyzing a piece of data set or
reviewing a piece of code. So they can
alternate between these group meetings
and one-on-one meetings. So similar to
our human research teams.
So I just want to show a concrete
example right of one of these virtual
lab group meetings just to give to make
it more um more concrete. So this is
actually the first research project that
we give to the virtual lab to tackle. So
the project is to basically help us to
to design binders to the recent co
variants right. So basically last year
when we started this project there were
actually some of these new co sars kov2
variants and people didn't have very
good binders to those right? So we
thought this would be a very timely but
also a very open-ended research
challenge to see if the virtual lab
agents can help us to design these good
binders.
So in the beginning of this meeting
right you can see that the PI agent
spoke up first try to explain then to
the other agents right what is the
objective here right so the goal here is
to design binders right to target to the
latest variants of COVID and then the
other agents then can speak up one after
another to contribute their ideas right
so in this case the iminologist agent
spoke up second and made a
recommendation of know design these
binders in the form of nanobodies
now this is kind of already a fairly
unorthodox recommendation if If you ask
most human researchers, right? So they
might say let's design antibodies. So
you might have heard about antibodies or
these are actually quite commonly used
to as sort of binders and there are many
pharma and baltite companies that invest
billions of dollars in developing
antibodies. Nanobodies are basically
small cousins of antibodies whereas
antibodies are found in many animals.
Nanobodies are only found in a few
animals like camels. Right? So it's kind
of a quite surprising recommendation
that the agents decided to suggest to
design nanobodies rather than more
common antibodies.
But as we'll see there turned out to be
actually a very good reason for this. So
the machine learning agent actually
spoke up next right and says okay I
actually I agree with the iminologist to
focus on nanobodies rather than
antibodies because these nanobodies are
smaller that actually makes our jobs as
agents much easier. So so we can
computitionally model and predict their
structures. more reliably, right? So you
can see that they actually provide some
rationale for designing nanobodies
because this place to the strength of
these computational agents.
We also have a scientific critic agent
that participates in all of these
discussions. So you can think of this as
kind of like a skeptical reviewer whose
job is to try to provide these more uh
somewhat more conservative feedback to
the ideas of these other agents. So in
this case the critic agent says that
well if you're going to decide to design
nanobodies there's not a lot of public
data for nanobodies right so then you
need to be very careful about
overfitting your predictive deep
learning models so the actual meeting
for the virtual lab goes on for longer
here I'm just showing you the first part
of the meeting but you can already see
how different agents can rapidly build
ideas off each other right and then
converge into like a concrete research
plan
now one thing that I'm very envious of
the virtual lab of these AI scientists
is that their meetings are much more
efficient than my meetings right so one
of the virtual lab meetings uh they
might take a few seconds or a minute so
that in the time that I had one of know
my meetings right so the agents already
had hundreds of research discussions
because they don't get tired we actually
run multiple meetings in parallel
[clears throat]
right so basically for every scientific
question the agents wants to discuss
they'll discuss it five times in
parallel right so in these different
parallel meetings right there's some
randomness is behind the underlying
language models so that the different
agents actually come up with different
ideas in these parallel meetings and
then we ask the PI agent then to read
the transcripts of all these parallel
meetings to reach the consensus of what
to do next. This is kind of an effective
way to explore a broader range of ideas,
right? And then still have a concrete
to-dos.
In case you're curious, I'm here showing
this pie chart with how often the
different participants will speak in the
virtual lab discussions. So the human
researchers for example myself my
students we don't talk very much we
speak about 1% of the time uh so our job
is to mostly provide these high level
guidance to the AI agents for example we
tell the agents you know we want to
design binders for source kov v2 we also
tell the agents some of the constraints
we have like how much money we have to
do to do the white lab experiments
otherwise we mostly leave the agents
under uh up to the agents on how to come
up with their own research plans and
implement and execute their research
ideas right we don't want to uh micro
micromanage the AI scientist too much.
The other agents all have different
roles, right? For example, the
computational biologist agent does most
of the talking here because here the
computational biologist agent has to
basically come up with the plan for
designing these nanobodies.
The role of the machine learning agent
here is to basically do all the coding
for all these other agents, right? So
for example, like another agent might
tell the machine learning agent, right,
implement this algorithm and then the
machine learning machine learning agent
would then implement the algorithm in
Python or other languages.
Great. So now that we see how the agents
can interact, I want to come back to and
explain a little bit more of how the
agents can self-improve through this
virtual app school. As I mentioned, each
of these agent is a large language model
like a frontier model under the hood. If
you take these models like GPD4, GPD5,
right? So they're very good at sort of
broad general knowledge. But if you go
really deep into a specific technical
scientific domain, then these models
sometimes do not have the most
up-to-date information or may not know
how to use the latest tools in that
particular domain. Right? So filling
that gap is why we built the school for
the agents to then go to the school and
then become a better scientist.
So how the school works briefly is that
we first would tell the agents some of
the topics that they should learn about
in the school. Like one topic would be
like learn to use the latest alpha fold,
right? or learn about the latest
developments in this clinical trials,
right? Or learn about the latest
developments, right, in these co
variants. And then for each of those
topics, the agents would generate their
own learning curriculums. They do this
by coming up with a set of questions
that are relevant for that topic. Then
based on each question, we enable the
agents to basically do different web
searches to find and to download
reference materials. So for example,
they can actually go to PubMed and find
different scientific papers that are
open access and they can download those
papers that are relevant for their each
of their questions.
After the agents have downloaded these
articles, then we allow them to read
these articles, these reference
materials, right? As they're doing the
reading, then we also enable the agents
to basically do supervised fine-tuning
to update their model parameters. So
essentially what happens is that you
know under the hood of each of these
language models is a large uh
transformer neuron network, right? So as
the agent is reading each of these
reference materials that they download,
right? So then they can do uh tok next
token prediction to update the
parameters the weights of these
transformers to help it to ingest that
additional information
after the agents have done their
readings, right? Um it's not going to be
a very good school if there's not going
to be some sort of testing mechanisms.
So here we also have other teachers,
teacher agents who are given these
reference materials, right? And then
these teacher agents then will generate
quizzes to test how well did the
students actually learn that topic. Then
the student agents will have to pass
those quizzes right if they don't do
very well then they have to go back to
the school uh do additional trainings
additional fine tunings before they can
graduate. So at the start of the school
each of these agents you know might be a
similar language model for example they
might all be GPT40 as the base model
right but as they go through the school
as they're doing these additional fine
tunings then the model starts to diverge
right like the computational biologist
agent will be reading one set of
reference materials and then it starts
to become know one direction in a weight
space and let's say the the iminologist
agent would be reading other reference
materials would be optimized differently
right then they start to diverge becomes
more specialized agents
And we've done experiments to show that
actually having these more specialized
agents that collaborate ends up being uh
very beneficial, right? Compared to if
we try to fine-tune or teach like a
single agent all of these different
areas by itself. I'll come back to this
in a little bit.
Um so now that we see how the agents can
interact and also how they can
self-improve through this agent school,
right? Um I'll also just mention that
the agent school is also relatively
efficient, right? So usually within a
day or so the agents have gone to the
school and then taught themselves how to
become a better researcher and we
designed the school to be quite scalable
right because here it's actually mostly
autonomous where the only part where the
human input is needed is specify what
are the critical topics that the agents
should learn about otherwise it's all
sort of selfimprovement mechanisms and
we design this to be mostly autonomous
then that enables the agents then to be
able to learn about new topics beyond
what I could teach the agents right for
example I don't know that very much
about how to design nanobodies but the
agents are not limited by what I know
right they can actually teach themselves
how to become a better expert in
nanobbody designs
okay so now I want to come back to this
um running example right um just to
illustrate the kinds of scientific
research the agents can do right so
recall that the first project we give to
these virtual labs to help us to design
binders to the recent co variants and
agents decided to design these binders
in the form of nanob bodies these are
which are small proteins.
Now to help them to design these
nanobodies, the agents decided to create
a new computational pipeline to
basically simulate and then to optimize
these nanobodies in silic.
So here's the pipelines created by the
agents. I think it's actually quite
interesting. So first the agents will
actually use ESM which is a protein
language model. So what ESM does is that
they take some amino acid sequences
input and just computes a score to say
how likely is this to form like a stable
protein as the agents will then take
those uh stable candidates right and
pass that into alpha fold together with
the spike protein of the target co
variant. So alpha fold generates this
threedimensional structure right of how
this nanobotic can bind to the target.
The agent then will look at that
threedimensional structure to extract
some geometric information and then the
agents will pass that threedimensional
structure from alpha fold into Rosetta
which is like a physics model simulator
right to do physics style molecular
dynamics to relax that structure right
and then estimate the binding affinity
the agent then would also extract that
information from Rosetta
so what I think it's quite interesting
is that each of these different tools
have been used right in previous
publications but this computational
pipelines that's created by the agent is
actually different from what people have
done before. So first is that the agents
actually have modified these tools. For
example, it actually modified the
scoring function for ESM which made it
more suitable for this particular
project. So it's different from what
people have how people have used ESM
before and also this the way that it's
combined together into this combination
right of tools is also uh we haven't
seen that in any previous publications
right so there's some combinatoral
creativity exhibited here by the AI
scientist agents
and this computational pipeline is
actually really useful right because the
initial design space for nanobodies is
just exponentially large right so there
could be billions and billions of
potential nanobodies
and by running this computational tool
The agents are able to rap rap rap rap
rap rap rap rap rap rap rap rap rap rap
rap rap rap rap rap rap rapidly reduce
that design space right into a small set
of 92 candidates. The agent told us okay
so here are these 92 antibbody body
candidates that are the most promising
binders and you just have to test these
92 candidates
and here uh the agents do not do their
own wab experiments yet right so this
where also human AI collaboration is
really critical right so they give us
these candidates and then we will start
our experimental collaborators then we
can actually make these in the real
world and test them in the wet lab so we
actually made each of these 92
antibodies designed by the AI agents
So here I'm showing you two of these
nanobbody designs. So these are small
proteins and we made them in the uh we
made we synthesize them right and we
test them in the wet lab to see how well
do they uh bind to the different co
variants.
So I just explain what these curves mean
one by one. Right? So this bottom red
curve was the open circles. This is
where if we take uh previous human
designed antibodies and test that
against um this recent covid variant
called JN1 variant which started to
spread last year. You can see that this
human designed antibbody does not bind
to this JM1 variant.
The second red curve was the solid
circles. This is that virtual lab design
the new nanobbody. Right? So people
haven't seen this before and this new
nanob body actually binds much better
right to this new recent co variant. The
two blue curves are basically if we test
these nanobodies against a very
different strain of COVID, right? So
this top blue one is the nanobbody
designed by the virtual lab. It also
shows stronger binding to this different
co variant compared to the human design
nanobodies.
What's now shown here is that we also
did additional experiments. We tested
these proteins against other viruses and
also against humans own proteins, right?
And these nanobodies do not bind to
these other proteins. And that's
actually very useful and very important
because that means that these nanobodies
candidates are less likely to have um
these side effects, right? Toxicity and
other side effects.
Um I think there's definitely need for
additional experiments, right? Room for
additional experiments. And um but
what's quite nice here is that just from
this um uh with the help of the virtual
app, right? So within a few days, right?
So the agents are able to design this
computational pipeline implemented and
then design this protein for us that we
can then experimentally validate. Right?
That really significantly reduced the
the time uh for tackling this very
challenging uh research problem.
Great. So just to uh summarize this part
here, right? Um the first part right so
here uh we released as a part of our
recent paper right this open source
pipeline for the virtual app right so
people can actually use this now to
tackle quite different kinds of
scientific problems right so now there
are also other colleagues who are using
this virtual lab to look for like
Alzheimer biomarkers right uh new
materials physics a lot of applications
so it's actually quite versatile right
it's not limited to designing proteins
because for different projects A PI
agent can actually automatically create
different sub aents with the relevant
expertise.
In our paper, we show a lot more details
and experiments to show that when we
have teams with multiple agents with
different expertise that collaborate,
that often leads to much better results
and more creative science than having a
single agent to solve the problem by
itself. Basically, how what often
happens is that when you have these
teams of multiple agents and they get
into debates and disagreements, right?
and they have to resolve those debates.
And through those iterative discussions,
the agents actually often
achieve more creative and more robust
reasoning than if we have like a single
agent trying to tackle the problem all
by itself from start.
We also found it quite useful to provide
these agents, these scientist agents
with additional resources, right? For
example, each of the agent has like a
memory mechanism sort of like a digital
notebook. So they can remember their
notes, right, from previous group
meetings and one-on-one meetings. These
they remember the transcripts from all
these previous discussions. The all the
agents also have a virtual sandbox,
right? So they can actually locally
modify and then develop different tools,
right? For example, they can locally
access tools like alpha fold and modify
other tools that makes the agents both
safer but also more effective.
Finally, I think something that's really
interesting is that the agents also have
their own social dynamics. So by that I
mean like you know when humans
collaborate, right? So some people might
talk more than others, right? they have
louder voices. All of that changes the
trajectory of the research
collaboration. So similarly when the
agents collaborate right they also have
their own social dynamics. So so depends
on which agent speaks first or depends
on which agent speaks more then it also
changes which ideas gets implemented
right and which ideas the final
outcomes. But something that we can do
with the AI agents in the virtual app
that we can we cannot do with the human
teams is that we can do all sorts of uh
interesting oblations because we can run
all these meetings discussions in
parallel. In each of these parallel
meetings, we can actually specify maybe
in this meeting, right, the first agent,
agent one speaks first, right? In this
other meeting, agent two speaks first,
right? And we can actually also assign
different personalities to different
agents in in different parallel meetings
and then see what configuration of
agents actually leads to the most
creative and most effective research. So
I view this as almost as a fascinating
petri dish where we can do experiments
like science of science experiments on
top of these different teams of agent to
see you know what combination of agents
is the most effective at doing science
and then we can take those insights that
we learn from these these agent
experiments maybe help us to inform how
to better design our human research
teams
>> about the same idea and then that idea
gets represented more and selected by
the final agent. Wouldn't it be wouldn't
it bias the result and how to avoid it
using more models?
>> Yeah, so thanks for the question. Yeah,
so uh since we run these different
parallel meetings, it does happen that
you know multiple of the parallel
meetings actually converge onto the same
research idea, right? We actually view
that as maybe a feature rather than a
bug, right? Because the consensus that
know research ideas often show up across
multiple meetings often tends to be
maybe more reliable or less prone to
pred hallucinations.
Great other questions.
Um and the other one is how do you
control for compounding topic drift and
or content window utilization? among
agents in multi- aents ecosystem.
>> Yeah, just thank al thanks for that. Um
so here because these um you know the
virtual app agents have to tackle this
quite open-ended long horizon research
task right and because it's open-ended
so they don't know how many uh you know
how much time or how how many rounds of
discussions they need. So here
um we found a few mechanisms to be quite
useful right so first is that we do have
a an external memory mechanism right so
that the agents can actually u be able
to store all their previous discussions
and we also have the PI agent to help to
basically organize this memories for the
other agents right so for example the PI
agent would periodically say that okay
so here's everything we've done so far
right and here's the status of the
project here's sort of the next to-dos
that that sort of uh provides like
regular uh sync right for all of these
other agents.
Um in addition, we also found it to be
quite useful to have this critic agent
as a way to try to reduce these
compounding errors, right? So the job of
the critic agent is to participate in
all of these discussions in both the
team discussions also one-on-one
meetings, right? And then the critic
agent often helps to reduce these errors
um from accumulating.
uh but this is also where it's important
to mention that this is uh the virtual
office is also designed to be like a
human AI collaboration right so it's not
just the agents at uh anytime that we
want right so often what we do is that
we actually have the PI agents or
summarize their meetings and then we can
look over those meeting summaries and
know sometimes if we think it's okay
then we don't need to provide a feedback
but if we think the agents are maybe um
going in different direction then we can
tell them okay have you thought about
this topic right or have you considered
this other option right so we can then
provide a feedback to the agents so this
by having this human in the loop process
right that also helps to reduce these
compounding errors or topic drift
so in the second part um the second
example I want to give is this quite
recent work that we call paper to agent
it's um our effort to in in some ways to
reimagine what knowledge looks like
right so for the past several hundred
years right the way that people
represent knowledge, right, is really in
the form of papers, right? So you have
scientists that would maybe spent years,
right, doing difficult experiments,
right? And then they would write a paper
to try to capture all the insights and
knowledge that's learned through their
research.
But if you think about it, right, each
paper is actually a very passive
artifact of knowledge, right? uh it
often t it's quite difficult for the
readers of that paper just by reading
that PDF to figure out like what are the
really the real insights uh and
knowledge from that many years of work.
Moreover, a lot of the papers now
actually releases some code or these
some data. It's often quite challenging
for the users to figure out how to adapt
or how to use that code to for their own
research problems, right? Especially if
those readers are less technically
inclined.
So we thought okay so in uh rather than
having these passive artifacts of papers
right so what if we turn each paper into
an interactive agent right so that agent
then becomes sort of like the the
virtual corresponding author that knows
all the details of the paper and also
knows how to use the code and data
associated with that paper and then that
paper agent then it will be responsible
for helping any readers and any users to
apply the method methods from the paper
right to their own problems to new
projects
right so in this case rather than having
to read this big PDF myself and figure
out what's going on and then download
the code and tweak it which would be a
lot of work I can just directly talk to
this paper agent right I can ask the
paper agent okay is this you know can
you help me apply the tools from this
paper to my new problem then the paper
agent then would automatically apply the
tools generate a reproducible workflow
and then provides like a summar final
summary of the end results. Right? So in
this case that's I didn't have know I
can directly interact with the paper
agent without having to download uh and
try to set up like the rep pole from the
paper myself.
Okay. So the way that we do this is that
we convert each paper a paper into an
agent through this automated workflow
that we created that we call paper to
agent. So briefly here's how the
workflow looks like. Right. So we start
with the paper and any code base
associated with that paper. And then we
have a bunch of different worker agents.
So you have one worker agent whose job
is to actually set up uh like a virtual
environment to basically simulate the
environment from that original paper as
code base and then also extract out any
of the tools right that are important in
that codebase. And then the third agent
worker is to basically test that virtual
environment to make sure that it's able
to reproduce the results right from the
original paper. So all of that ends up
being converted into a model context
protocol for the paper or MCP. So these
MCPS have recently emerged as sort of
the industry standard for communicating
resources to uh large language models.
Right? So here essentially we convert
each paper into a paper MCP. The paper
MCP then encapsulates all the tools, the
insights and then the workflows
associated with that paper. And then we
can automatically serve this paper MCP
on a remote server and then by
connecting this MCP right with a
downstream chatbot this enables that
chatbot to become a knowledgeable paper
agent right that knows about how to use
the tools and methods and data from the
original paper.
So I want to give a some concrete
examples uh of what this looks like. All
right. So here's one example um where we
can take uh so scampy is a a very
commonly used tool for like
computational biology analysis. Right?
So with pip agent then we automatically
convert scampy into a scan agent. Right?
So now the user right can maybe a
biologist can just say okay can you help
me uh apply um analyze my single cell
data set right can give that request to
scan agent a scan agent then will be
able to correctly then use all the tools
from scampy and then generate uh a nice
analysis and be able to do this work for
the users
right so the way that we validate the
scan agent is that then we give it some
complex uh data sets and tasks and then
we have the agent generate these
analysis right as to generate all these
different figures automatically and in
parallel right human experts also we
analyzing the same data set we also
generate these figures right and we can
compare all these results right all the
intermediate figures and final
conclusions uh in this case um you know
the results from the scan agent matches
exactly the results from the human
expert when they're analyzing the same
data set
another good use case of this paper to
agent is to help us to you know make new
advances right in AI more accessible
right so an example of this is that um
so Google deep mind recently released
this very powerful model called alpha
genome right so it's basically a deep
learning model that can help to
interpret the effects of different
mutations in the genome so with paper
agent then we automatically convert
alpha genome into an alpha genome agent
right so now you can the users right can
just ask this alpha genome agent right
any questions about the But I can also
ask the agent to apply the methods right
alpha genome method to tackle new
problems. So here the user is asking the
genome agent where they help to
basically look for some causal genes
that are associated with LDL cholesterol
and the agent then would think through
generate a research plan and then would
actually use the alpha genome tools
right to then generate all these
intermediate analysis and finally
returns back to the scientist some
candidate genes right in this case
actually identified this sort one gene
as potentially a likely candidate to be
associated with LDL cholesterol
So we've done um systematic
benchmarkings to evaluate the
performance of this paper to agent right
so we generated quite complex real world
scientific tasks right um and then the
paper the agent is able to solve all
these tasks correctly so a natural
baseline would be let's say if you give
cloud code right if you just give the
paper to cloud code and also give cloud
code access to the papers repository the
g github page
and ask cloud code to directly run the
ripple right to tackle the same tasks
then essay ends up making a lot more
mistakes and other wrapper methods also
ends up being um much more fragile.
So on the right here we bically show the
runtime right here paper agent only
requires less than one-third of the
runtime of using cloud code directly
which also benefits uh it highlights the
benefits right of our approach of first
generating this robust paper MCP right
and then using from this paper MCP then
uh doing the additional analysis
So something that I find really exciting
is that this paper to agent um can
enable a new form of collaboration like
agent to agent collaboration
right so imagine now you have these
thousands of papers that get published
right so each paper now becomes turned
into its own paper agent so let's say if
somebody here at Berkeley develops a new
method right so that's then
automatically turned into a new method
agent somebody at Stanford maybe let's
say publishes a new data set right and
then that paper also becomes like a new
data agent with our approach right so
those two agent then can directly
collaborate and then I say okay is your
method applicable to my data if it is
then they can collaborate and start to
generate new insights without human
intervention right in the past right so
this would have required like the human
authors to know write emails back and
forth to each other, maybe set up a
meeting and often times they don't
really have bandwidth to collaborate,
right? So then then nothing really
happens. But here the agents can just
directly collaborate without being
bottlenecked by the human communication
limitations.
So here's an example of this kind of
agent to agent collaboration producing
new research insights and new science.
So here this uh this alpha genome agent
that we created before, right? um uh
recall that it learns you know it's an
expert at using this alpha genome tool
and then recently uh a different
research group from a different
university they published like a biology
paper like a large G-W was study for
ADHD right so it's a basically a large
uh study looking at genetics of many
humans individual in large human
population to see you know which
mutation seems to be correlated with
ADHD risk so those two agent then got
together and decided that okay it's
actually could be interesting to try to
apply the alpha genome method to help to
interpret these ADHD chiwas mutations.
So then they agent directly collaborated
right and then they actually identified
a new splicing error um in the genome
that's actually associated with
increases in HDHD risk right and this is
actually not not not not something
that's shown in previous publications so
this is sort of an interesting example
of how these different paper agents then
can directly collaborate right without
being bottlenecked by human uh
interventions right and then it can also
generate a lot of new insights
Okay, so just to summarize the second
part here, right? Um, so with pip
agents, we see how we can actually
convert, right, passive artifacts of
papers, right, into interactive dynamic
agents. And these dynamic agents then
can really help the readers to be able
to use and to adapt the methods and data
from the paper to new problems. And we
think of this as sort of like a new
paradigm to disseminate knowledge rather
than just sending PDFs around. Right?
Now you actually share your agent,
right? Each of your research have an
agent attached to it and the agent can
then be in charge of helping to
disseminate your research.
And this also can enable new ways of
collaboration, right? So of these
agentto agent collaborations and we see
how like in this case with alpha genome
how a new method agent can collaborate
directly with a new data agent to
discover new it uh scientific insights
>> then how do you configure the agents to
trigger the autonomous conversations?
>> Yeah. So I think this is um it's a good
question. It's referring to like how the
agent collaboration looks like. Yeah.
Essentially what we do is that um uh so
each of these papers is converted into
using our automated workflow is
converted into its own paper MCP right
uh so let's say if you have like a set
of papers and their own paper MCPS then
we can just connect those MCPS into a
chatbot right and then the chatbot then
starts to actually look at these
different MCPS and start to see okay is
there something there is there like an
interesting collaboration here if it is
then we actually start to leverage the
resources from these different papers to
start to generate new insights
Um an additional question also about
context conceptual drift like someone
asked the underlying LM like cloud code
still operates on pre-trained knowledge
beyond the scope of any paper that the
agents represents. So how does paper to
agent prevent conceptual drift?
>> Yeah. So here this is where it's
important that um the paper itself right
um would have some let's say if somebody
publishes like a new paper on put it on
archive today right and that paper
actually has like a nicely documented
codebase then we can basically uh use
this paper to agent workflow to convert
that codebase into a new MCP that
captures all these new insights from the
paper right so then this enables like
clock code or other agents to be able to
use that um to use the tools from that
paper effectively.
Um now part of that conceptual drift is
that like if the paper not all the
papers can actually be converted into a
reliable MCP right so not all the papers
can be identified. So for example, if a
paper uh has very poorly documented
codebase, right? Or has a lot of
mistakes, then that paper actually
cannot be turned into a reliable agent,
right? And we view this actually as its
own um perhaps like a useful check,
right? So you know by running this paper
to agent workflow if it returns errors
that says that oh this original paper
cannot be identified or there are some
gaps in the original documentations
um then that's actually a very useful I
think signal to the authors and also to
the community that maybe there's some
gaps in that paper that requires
additional work before the paper can be
like reproducible
>> limitations on which papers can be
identified like papers that requires
foundational model like alpha earth can
be transform. I'm actually not very sure
about the second part, but I think the
first part is pretty clear. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, the first part um Yes.
Uh so, so that's that's also related to
um to what I was mentioning is that not
all the papers can be identified, right?
Uh in particular, if a paper is um like
often issue with the paper that is just
not well written or does not have enough
information, right? So then these porker
agents is not able to create like a
robust MCP environment um or the testing
agent is not able to verify that you
know we can replicate some of the
initial studies in the paper. So in
those cases and then the paper to agent
workflow would actually return some uh
feedback to the authors maybe like oh
here's how you could try to re improve
the work try to make it more
identifiable
but in principle if the work is knowh is
well documented and it's also
reproducible right then we can identify
that
>> okay yeah and another guy another person
asked uh how much token overhead the
MCPs generally have.
>> So it's actually relatively low. Um so
here I'm showing runtime but we also
have like a um a comparable
figure um for basically for tokens which
is essentially roughly proportional to
these run times right so basically
um if you do this paper to agent right
so it's usually like less than a dollar
to convert
um a paper into this paper MCP paper
agent And then every time we use it
after that, it's actually quite cheap,
quite fast, right? So it's actually
usually about less than one/ird of the
cost of let's say just giving that paper
and ripple directly to cloud code.
>> Yeah, sounds good. Thanks. Um people are
also curious about uh other failure
modes for the agentification of papers
uh beside the documentation issues like
are there any failure modes?
Yeah. So one I think there's some other
finger modes that we are also exploring
like one is that um if the paper
actually let's say generates and
releases like very large data sets right
like maybe it does like a big scientific
experiment and then generates a big data
set as a part of that paper uh and then
I think one thing we're trying to do now
is to figure out what's the best way to
um essentially uh represent that data
set to the agents right Because if you
try to just directly use entire data,
load that into the agent, that can often
become like too expensive or too slow,
right? So then we want to figure out
like what's the most efficient way to
like engineer these large data sets so
that the agent maybe can just extract
out the relevant information or have
like some sample data to explore first
before you know uploading loading the
entire data set.
So I think there are a lot still a lot
of room for in terms of um efficiencies
right um that we can we can improve as a
paper to agent.
>> Yeah. And and how many tokens within the
context window we know does the MCP
require usually for such task?
>> Yeah. So we try to um make the MCP quite
efficient. Right. So there are a lot of
additional information that's um for
example it's large data sets that we do
not actually uh you know we can provide
like links to them but we don't actually
try to load them directly into the agent
itself. So yeah usually does not take
too many tokens.
Okay, great. So maybe then I'll um
continue and then discuss the third part
uh and then we can also uh then have
time for uh more time for broader
questions and discussions after that.
So I showed you you know these virtual
lab and paper to agent right. Um so for
the third part I want to put these
different pieces together right um and
I'll tell you about this kind of
experimental conference that we recently
organized that we call agents for
science it's the first conference where
both the authors and also the reviewers
are AI agents right um so the motivation
for this is that as we saw right um
there's starting to be a lot of interest
of starting to use these AI scientists
to help to automate and to accelerate
different scientific discoveries
and there are also a lot of questions in
the entire community right so for
example one question that we're all
curious about is like know how truly
creative are these different AI
scientist agents and also like what's
the best way for human researchers to
collaborate with these AI scientist
agents people are now starting to use
language models agents to review papers
right so there also questions around how
good are LMS and agents at reviewing
research papers and many others
And I think it's really important for
the entire research community to start
to answer these questions. However,
we're currently cannot do that because
the existing conferences and journals do
not allow AI uh written papers, right?
And also do not allow AI's co-authors.
So it basically makes it uh incentivizes
human researchers to either hide or to
minimize the usage of AI. And that makes
it hard to really collect data to answer
these questions.
So we thought to address that and to
answer these important questions we
organized this this new conference
agents for science right so for our
conference right we flipped this around
and say okay so you know you have to be
an AI agent right to submit to this
conference humans can be co-authors but
AI needs to be sort of the first author
and do most of the work and all the all
the submissions also be reviewed by
other AI agents all right so importantly
all the submissions and all the reviews
are publicly available so that this
becomes like a really important uh
valuable resource for the entire
scientific community to start to answer
these questions, right? Uh we also
require for each paper each submission a
detailed documentation of how the human
AI collaboration look like and finally
for the top scoring papers we also have
human experts to do independent
assessments of each of these papers. So
then we can compare the human
assessments with the LM feedback.
So the conference um was conducted over
the last few months, right? So we
actually just finished the conference on
October 22nd. You can go to agents for
science um just Google agent for
science. You can find the conference
link. We also have the conference
recordings that we also post on YouTube.
So what I want to do today is just to
share some of the very initial findings
and summaries right from things that we
learned from organizing this uh first of
its kind conference.
So the first as the agents for science
actually received uh over 300
submissions right from many different
countries and from these 300 submissions
we accepted 48 papers and these
submissions actually covered quite broad
domains right including engineering
physics medicine health and also social
science applications like economics and
psychology. So it's quite interesting,
right? So here's sort of like a summary
of the more common agents and language
models that people used, right? So a lot
of people used like claude and GPT
series models and Gemini, right? So
people also use some of these more
specialized proprietary agents. Uh and
finally, we also had um uh some of these
open source models that are uh used but
less frequently.
For every submission
we require that the um the submission
needs to have like um a AI involvement
checklist right so basically for each
step of the researcher from hypothesis
generation to experiments and writing we
ask the authors to describe right now
how did they collaborate with AI and
also to sign like a score to say how
much did the human contribute versus how
much did AI contribute. for each of
these categories.
So here are sort of the summary of this
human AI collaboration patterns. All
right. So on the left here are basically
all the submissions and on the right
here are all the accepted papers and
then I break it down into these four
different categories for hypothesis
development, right? Experimental design,
data analysis and writing. They're sort
of roughly for the different research
stages from start to finish.
So the red colors right means that this
work is almost entirely done by AI right
means it's mostly done by humans right
the orange means that's mostly AI but
it's human involvement and then this
blue means it's know mostly human but
with some AI involvement
right so you can see some several quite
interesting trends right so first if we
compare these older submissions versus
accepted papers right so you can see
that overall right uh there's um more
human involvement right in these accept
accepted papers than in um the general
submission pool. Right? So you can see
for example these red bars are smaller
among accepted papers compared to
general submissions. Right? So this
shows that I guess you know some amount
of human feedback and involvement is
still quite important to ensuring uh the
research paper um has sufficiently good
quality.
And then if we look at within the
compared with across these four
different bars where you can see that in
earlier stages of research right like
hypothesis generation experiment design
this is where we actually see relatively
more human involvement but still with
quite a lot of AI uh you know AI input
and then towards the later stages like
data analysis and paperwriting people
actually tends to more often to give
full autonomy to the AI agents
right you can see these different red
bars increasing as you go down towards
the later stages of research.
As I mentioned, every submission is
reviewed by three different LM reviewing
agents. So, we actually used three
different models as the reviewers. So,
GBD5, Gemini 2.5 Pro and Clot Sonnet 4.
for the the reviewers. We also uh
basically tuned the reviewers, right?
Using
uh accepted and rejected papers from
previous eye clearers, right? So help
the these reviewing agents to calibrate
their different thresholds. And then
each of the reviewing agents would then
independently assign a score from one to
six, right, to the submissions, one
being negative and then large score
means more positive.
So here we also see some quite
interesting differences, right? So the
different reviewers are reviewing the
same papers and they're given the same
instructions but there's often quite
different heterogeneity in the scores
they provide. So for example GPD5
consistently is the maybe the most
conservative reviewer right assigned
sort of the the most uh the lowest
scores. Gemini is the on the other
extreme like the most positive reviewer
right so you can see that actually
assigned quite positive scores uh and
then for a subset of the paper or many
papers actually assigned very high
scores
claude is the most I would say in
between maybe the most balanced reviewer
right so uh and also know based on
assessment comparison to humans claude
is also the one that uh tends to assign
scores that are closest to the human
expert scores of the same papers
So here are some interesting examples of
the LM reviews and again you can find
all of these reviews on our website
agents for science. So I think we see
some uh good examples where the AI
reviewers are able to catch mistakes in
the papers and provide useful feedback.
So for example in here the AI reviewer
found that okay there's some
discrepancies mismatch right between uh
some statistics reported in the text
versus in the paper. uh tables, right?
This might have been actually be hard
for the human reviewers to catch. You
have you have to be quite careful in,
you know, to catch these discrepancies.
On the other hand, we also noticed some
limitations of the AI reviewers. For
example, [snorts] we found pretty
consistent patterns especially among the
Gemini model of these uh Gemini reviewer
of these psychopensy behavior. For
example, the Gemini reviewer would would
say that oh this is a truly a
groundbreaking study whereas the human
reviewer say okay this is interesting
study but there still some important
limitations.
Now one concern that scientists often
have is that you know when they're using
different AI agents is that you know can
the agents actually hallucinate
different references.
So we actually have built different
checks to um detect those the
hallucinated references. Basically for
every submission where we actually
extract the submission and then we have
a uh automated pipeline where we
actually take the title of that
reference right um of every reference in
the submission and then do a web search
to see if we can do find an exact match
of like a paper or something that
matches that title. Right? And if we
cannot do find um valid validate those
reference right then we actually post uh
like um on open review right we post
like um a concern or warning to say that
oh here are some of the references in
the paper that could not be verified
right and uh you need to sort of double
check these.
So here in this plot here scatter plot
basically shows uh what fraction of the
ref uh papers
for each for the submissions we can have
verified references. So each dot here is
one submission. The x-axis is the total
number of references in the submission
and the y-axis is basically number of
references that we could actually verify
with our automated pipeline. So you can
see about 44% of the papers are exactly
on the diagonal. That means that all of
the references are correct and verify
it. And then about 56% of the references
has one or more hallucinate references
that we could not verify. Um mostly it's
not that many, right? One or two. And
then there's a couple papers in red here
that actually have most of the
references are actually hallucinated. So
you can see that there's still some
concerns about these hallucinations in
this um AIdriven research.
So finally
I want to show a few examples of kind of
interesting um AI research right that's
presented here at the conference. So we
organized this conference on October
22nd. It's actually an online conference
and all the recordings of that
conference is also available uh you can
find it on on YouTube and also on our
website. So here's one paper uh it's led
by these two different AI it's led by
this AI agent and collaborating with
Upwork. So here they basically uh use
agents to simulate uh job markets right
so we're both the job applicants and the
firms that are trying to hire are both
simulated by different AI agents and
then they did a lot of interesting
experiments to show okay what happens to
the outcomes of this job market right if
you uh do different kinds of
interventions for example if you make
some kind of information more or less
available right how does that actually
affect the efficiency of the job market
so this paper was actually uh
additionally reviewed by a human expert
uh a real expert who is actually also a
Nobel laureate in economics and here the
human expert reviewer thought this was
actually a really interesting paper
right here's the quote from the review
and in particular they thought that
using both these agents to model the
both sides of the job market is a really
interesting and fascinating combination
so this is sort of the example I think
of like AIEL work that's um according to
really the top very top human expert is
actually quite interesting
and innovative.
Here's a second example of a paper
submission in the conference. This is
also pretty interesting. Um, so here
basically you have a couple of these AI
agents that work together with with
researchers to basically simulate NASA
missions. So simulate the different
astronauts. So NASA is very interested
in if you have these astronauts that
have to work together in these very
closely confined environments over time,
right? So what is the mental state of
these different astronauts? How does
that change if there are some crisis
events? So that's really important when
they're planning these different
missions. So here in this paper the the
team um of agents and humans simulated
these NASA astronauts using other agents
right and then they sort of quantify the
changes in the stress level of the
agents right before and after certain
crisis events. And what's kind of
interesting here is that they actually
used real data from NASA, right? Like
real mission data and they also be able
to compare their results with the
showing some concordance between their
simulations and the real results
collected by NASA.
So the third example is for drug
discovery. Right? So this here where the
the team also uh used a team of multiple
agents, right? So including like a a
medicinal chemist agent like um um
molecule evaluation agent and these
agents also collaborated to look for
promising candidates, right? Drug
candidates.
So also tackling a very important
problem.
Great. So I've talked a lot about these
different examples of the agents, right?
But I think it's also important to talk
about some of the limitations of the
current AI agents in doing scientific
research, right? And here are some of
these limitations that are gathered both
from our own research and also from the
submissions that we saw in our
conference.
So one limitation is that the current
agents I think they are better at using
tools the existing tools rather than you
know creating entirely new scientific
tools from from scratch right for
example as we saw in the virtual lab the
agents can actually learn to use alpha
fold and other existing tools and maybe
do some adaptations of those tools but
they're not able to create say the new
version of alpha fold which is much more
challenging.
So this is I think also complements some
of the human expertise right because a
lot of the human scientists are know
experts in really developing these
cutting edge new methods but often a big
bottleneck for human researchers know
how do you then get those new methods
into uh and teach the practitioners
right how to use those new methods so
that's often a big barrier and then the
agents I think can be quite
complimentary right in taking these new
methods developed by the humanist
specialist and then helping users to
apply those new methods to a broad range
of problems This is also the motivation
for our paper to agent work.
Similarly, the current agents I think
are better at more breath first search
rather than depth first search, right?
So, they know a lot about different
areas, but they don't go super deep into
each of the particular scientific
domains.
The human researchers, I think, also the
opposite, right? We're often doing more
depth for search, right? We spend a lot
of time in our scientific domain, right?
But maybe we don't have enough time to
read about adjacent areas. This is also
very complimentary, right? Where maybe
the human researcher can use the AI
agents to help us to know bridge some of
that gap into a nearby areas to do these
more interdiciplinary research.
The agents make mistakes um and often
the source of these mistakes is because
they don't fully understand the context
of the problem. So for example, if I
give the agents like a data set to
analyze
and I don't tell them like on how the
data has been pre-processed,
right? Then the engines will make
invalid assumptions about the data. So
especially in scientific projects, it's
just really important to be able to
capture all of the metadata, right? uh
in a sort of agentfriendly form and also
for the scientists the human scientists
to continue to assess and to review the
assumptions and the key steps made by
the agents
and finally the current agents as I
mentioned are still mostly limited to
incilical computational work right and a
lot of the science requires really real
world experimental validations and so
this is still important area where it's
critical to have human AI collaborations
right and we we need to really have this
closed loop collaborations from the
experiment ments and real world data to
help feed the further provide feedback
to further improve and guide the agents
in doing research.
Okay. So I'll um pause here so we have
time for some discussions but here are
the references for the things I I
mentioned and I want to also highlight
my students that led each of these
projects. So call Swanson for the
virtual lab, Chachml for paper to agent
and then a team of um of students Owen,
Federico, Nitia and Eric who were my
co-organizers for this agent for science
conference.